Empresses in the Palace—the Legend of Zhen Huan
Adapted from the novel by Liu Lian Zi
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: Unfortunate Love
I can cut a thousand strands of hair
but I cannot sever the tangled threads of my mind.
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Bowing with my hands clasped, I give away my throne.
Lowering my head, devoted to the beauty by my side.
The wheel of fate turns, granting blessings or misfortune.
Will it be destiny’s trial or reward?
Heaven’s will cannot be known,
weaving together weals and woes.
For lovers caught in eternal time,
who can break the spell of romance?
Who can break the spell of romance?
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Your Highness, Jingbai's tongue has been cut out.
Reward it to Gūwalgiya.
Aye.
Having this tongue
will teach her to manage her own.
What a vicious heart you have!
I owe this idea to Concubine An.
Wen Shichu!
Even if this wretch doesn't have secret feelings for you,
Do you swear you don't hold feelings
in your heart for her?
Do you dare swear on your clan and parents
that you have no aberrant feelings
for this concubine of His Majesty?
My Lady,
are you delirious?
Delirious?
Do you think His Majesty and I are both blind?
Your affection for Noble Consort Lumiere has been unveiled.
Dr. Wen, I heard you haven't married yet!
My marital status...
is not of your concern, My Lady.
Your Majesty, Your Majesty!
I have always been faithful to you, Your Majesty.
I have served you for so many years.
Why do you only care about this wretch
who offended you?
Your Majesty.
Your Majesty...
Take her away.
Your Majesty. Your Majesty!
Your Majesty!
Your Majesty.
Wen Shichu, each day you stay by her side,
you will be digging her grave for her!
I'll keep my eyes open to witness that day!
Your Majesty!
Dr. Wen, you must know that
your very being,
and your affection,
will cause fatal consequences to others.
Your Majesty,
Your Highness,
I will vindicate myself in my own way.
Take this filthy thing away.
It's been a long day.
I'm exhausted.
The Empress must be as well.
You have always had a weak constitution.
Moving forward, everything in the palace
will be overseen by Noble Consort Lumiere.
Your Majesty...
With assistance from Consort Honnête and Concubine Estime.
You will ...
only need to take care of your health.
Don't push yourself beyond your ability.
With the two of you assisting with the palace affairs,
I can rest assured.
I thank Your Majesty.
Your Majesty.
Imperial Doctor Wen... He...
Speak calmly.
Doctor Wen turned himself into a eunuch.
He's in critical condition.
My Lady, my Lady!
Imperial doctors! Imperial doctors!
- How is he?
- Quick!
Hold on!
Take the medicine now! Quickly!
Push, My Lady!
My Lady, push!
My Lady, it's almost crowning!
My Lady, push! My Lady!
My Lady. My Lady!
The baby's coming, push! My lady!
Almost there, My Lady.
Push harder, My Lady!
How is it? You must hold on!
Immediately!
Bring more White Bleeding Powder!
It will save his life!
Yes.
Hurry up, hurry!
Push, My Lady! Push!
Push, My Lady! Almost out!
Here! Keep going!
Hold on! My Lady!
My Lady, hold on!
Push, My Lady!
Yes, push. Push!
My Lady!
Why is she bleeding so much?
Bring hot water, hot water!
- Hurry!
- Yes.
My Lady!
Hot water coming!
Hot water!
Make way for hot water!
My Lady, hold on!
What shall we do?
So much blood!
You knew Meizhuang was pregnant,
and should not be disturbed.
Yet your messenger came here to the Palace of Pearl Jade.
Lingrong,
Was your purpose a spiteful one?
Lumière, I wasn't aware.
Please don't blame me.
I didn't know my servant did this.
Please do believe me, Lumière.
Sparrow mustn't have meant any harm.
Had I known it would come to this,
I'd rather suffer in Meizhuang's stead.
Lumière,
we entered the palace together, I...
Whether deliberate or unintentional -
I won't mind if the mother and the child are safe.
If half a hair goes amiss,
this will never end for you.
You're right to slap me, Lumière.
It's my fault to have failed to discipline my servant,
causing this disaster as vast as Heaven.
Sparrow, come in here!
Peace to Your Highness.
You dare to say "peace"?!
Your Highness, I admit my fault!
You disturbed the peace of Concubine Vertu!
Are you intentionally making me feel guilt-ridden?
My Lady, please care for your body.
Your Highness, please spare me!
My years of sisterhood with Meizhuang -
all ruined by your hooves startling her!
If anything goes wrong with Meizhuang,
I'll take my own life with her!
Why would I still care for my body?
You and your big mouth!
- Damn you, you big-mouthed slave!
- Your Highness, I won't dare do it again!
The servant didn't behave properly;
But Concubine An should not break rules.
- Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
- Peace to Your Majesty.
The servant broke the rules.
Drag her to some secluded place and flog her to death.
Su Peisheng.
Yes.
Guards.
Your Majesty, please spare my life!
I admit my fault!
I'll never do it again!
Your Majesty, please spare my life!
Take her.
I'll never do it again!
Your Majesty, please spare my life!
Push, Your Highness!
Push, My Lady!
My Lady, My Lady!
Almost there! My Lady, hold on!
Your Majesty,
Dr. Wen's bleeding has stopped.
He will survive.
It's just...
Speak.
He is now like the eunuchs in the palace.
He'll never be able to have children.
I see.
Why is Concubine Vertu still in labor?
Your Majesty, don't worry.
Your Majesty,
Concubine Vertu was startled,
and her prenatal qi is greatly destabilized.
The situation is dire.
My skill is shallow in this area,
and Her Highness's pregnancy
has always been under Dr. Wen's care.
I have no information on her past medical conditions.
It's as if my hands are locked, Your Majesty.
What about the child? How is it?
Her Highness has the potential to bleed to death.
She has already lost so much blood that she has no strength to push.
The child's head is stuck.
I gave Her Highness Guchong soup to consume,
but the situation did not improve.
I don't know about Her Highness's constitution,
so I don't dare use herbs to stop bleeding
If Dr. Wen were here...
Dr. Wen has regained consciousness.
But given his health condition,
I'm afraid he cannot help deliver the baby.
Even though he cannot walk,
we can bring him in with a stretcher.
Dr. Wen may not be able to aid in Her Highness's labor,
but he understands Her Highness's constitution.
We could discuss the medication together.
It's already a sin that Dr. Wen became implicated;
if this harms the safety of Meizhuang and her baby,
the outcome would be unimaginable.
Carry Wen Shichu in here.
Yes.
Shifu, shifu!
Wei Lin ... Wei Lin
Wei Lin.
Concubine Vertu has always had a warm constitution.
But now ...
qi and blood have become reversed,
causing obstructed labor.
Quickly!
Use mountain ginseng to preserve her consciousness.
And then use the Shengju Tonifying Soup. Hurry!
Understood. Go prepare these right now!
Bring me the herbs.
Shifu.
This is the labor tonic.
What did you say we should add?
- Salty plums, seven salty plums.
- Salty plums.
- Burn them to ashes.
- Burnt to ashes.
- And aged pagoda tree flowers, one tael.
- Aged pagoda tree flowers.
- Burned grass, half a tael.
- Black soot.
Grind to powder.
- Mix these herbs into wine and then warm it ...
- Yes.
by quenching a red-hot metal weight in the wine.
Hurry!
Understood. Prepare it immediately!
Your Majesty, Her Highness took the medicine Dr. Wen prescribed.
Her Highness's bleeding has lessened.
Now she has more strength to push.
Don't worry, Your Majesty.
Meizhuang's kindness ensures Heaven will aid her.
You, go tell Concubine Vertu:
Announce my decree:
Concubine Vertu is now promoted to Consort Vertu.
So she can give birth with a peaceful mind.
Yes.
I'm in so much debt to Meizhuang.
After she gives birth safely,
I'll make it up to her.
Congratulations to Your Majesty.
Consort Vertu just gave birth to a princess.
Marvelous! Wonderful news!
How is Meizhuang?
My Lady is too tired to even speak.
Let me check on Consort Vertu.
My Lady just gave birth and is very tired.
Perhaps Your Majesty can let her rest for a moment.
Your Majesty had a long day.
You should go back and get some rest now.
Visit Meizhuang when she has regained her energy.
I'll stay here for her.
Your Majesty can rest assured.
All right.
But you should get some rest too.
Don't over exert yourself.
Let me accompany Your Majesty back.
I bid Your Majesty goodbye.
That's so wonderful!
Now Your Highness is relieved.
Drink some tea.
Terrible ... Terrible news!
My Lady is bleeding heavily!
How is it?
Bring White Bleeding powder quickly!
No need.
Who said no need? Who said it?
Bring the best medicine here!
I'll kill all of you if Meizhuang is not saved!
Yes.
Huan'er.
Meizhuang.
Don't cry.
I just want to talk to you.
Tell them all to leave.
You all may leave.
Wen Shichu...
will stay.
My child.
How small she is.
So soft.
Yes.
But she'll grow up so fast.
Just look how quickly Hongyan and Lingxi have grown.
Meizhuang,
His Majesty wants you to be safe.
He already promoted you to Consort Vertu.
Are you enjoying being Noble Consort Lumiere?
If being a Noble Consort, at the center of his favor,
is still flavorless and empty,
why would I ...
care about being Consort Vertu?
I know you don't care about the rank, Meizhuang.
But "the child becomes distinguished
by the esteem granted to the mother."
You need to think about her future.
My child .. she won't care about these things.
Shichu ...
Have you held the baby?
You ... should hold her.
Your Highness ...
I don't dare.
You're still blaming me ... aren't you?
For that night...I was also to blame.
Don't bear the burden of blame.
Today you mutilated yourself with a knife;
isn't it because of your deep regret?
I know,
I know you resent me
for that night.
The Empress Dowager bestowed the wine upon His Majesty and me,
and I coaxed you to drink it with me.
Causing you to have this lifelong loss.
Meizhuang ...
you were so foolish.
I am ... close to dying.
What's there to be afraid of?
I'm so happy that ... I was able to indulge myself once.
I have no regret in this life.
Huan'er.
All these years, only Shichu and you have been
genuinely good to me.
But Shichu ... he holds you in his heart.
So his kindness towards me has always been...
because of you.
Meizhuang...
Shichu,
I wish to ... ask you this ...
All these years,
have you ever
felt a shred of
true affection towards me?
Even just ... in the slightest?
Forget it.
I'd rather you not answer
than
tell me a lie out of pity
for my death.
That night ... the wine alone ...
would not have been enough to stir my emotions.
So ...
My kindnesses towards you...
were never only because of Huan'er.
Is that true?
Hearing you say that ...
I ...
I'm so happy.
Meeting you in this life ...
I have no regrets over it.
Shichu,
will you ...
hold ... our baby ...?
Will you?
Yes. I will.
Huan'er.
The baby hasn't been given a name, right?
Jinghe.
[Jing: tranquil; He: peaceful]
How about ... naming her Jinghe?
A peaceful life through the tranquil months and years.
Isn't that all we looked forward to?
Don't cry. Please don't cry.
Although I'm no longer physically complete,
you and I ... will for ever and ever be together.
No one will defame you and I
the way they defamed Noble Consort Lumière.
Shichu,
please take good care of our child, watching her grow.
Don't allow ... anyone to mistreat her.
Huan'er,
please help Shichu take care of the baby.
Also, of the Empress and Lingrong ...
you both must be vigilant ...
of them.
I feel so tired.
How fortunate …
I...
I have ... never been like this ...
resting ...
in your ...
arms ...
As sunlight streams through the bedside folding screen,
her hair at the temples curls over her snow-white cheeks.
Sleepily she paints her eyebrows slim,
taking her time to bathe and dress.
When she puts on a flower between mirrors,
to tell her face from the flower is difficult.
The new patch on her brocade vest
[The Palace of Pearl Jade]
is two love birds in gold thread.
The new patch on her brocade vest
[The seat of Meizhuang of the Shen family]
Sleepily she paints her eyebrows slim,
taking her time to bathe and dress.
When she puts on a flower between mirrors,
to tell her face from the flower is difficult.
The new patch on her brocade vest
is two love birds in gold thread.
Is two love birds in gold thread.
Lord XVII is the one with Venerable Prince Shen.
Isn't he outstanding?
Jade, you don't need to follow me.
Please go back to serve my sister.
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
Follow us to get updates on the translation progress.
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
What's the matter?
Did you not have time to change your clothes?
Are you not aware your sleeve is ripped?
You are very observant.
Here, I'll stitch it up for you,
to repay you for
defending my sister yesterday.
But...
Don't talk.
All done.
You can't talk when your clothes are being sewn,
or else you will marry a savage wife
who curses you every day.
But you just talked.
I'm done sewing.
It's not perfect,
but it's definitely better than what you had before.
Great!
It looks like a lively centipede.
No other lady ever sews clothes for me,
only my mother.
My mother is Concubine Dowager Harmonie.
She used to work at the Embroidery Department.
Your mother treats you well.
She must care a lot about you.
Please take the medicine, Princess.
Here...
Come here ... Here...
How can the Princess recover
if she doesn't take the medication?
Look at her, even her cry is weak.
The Princess is too young.
It's hard to feed her medicine.
She will spit it out even if we feed it to her.
Then let the wet nurses take it and convert the medicine to breast milk.
We'll give it to the Princess that way.
This is feasible.
Your Highness, Consort Vertu has passed away.
You should take care of your health even in the deepest grief.
I've been having dreams every night.
Dreaming about the time with Meizhuang
before we entered the Palace.
I feel that ... she's still nearby ...
Your Highness has slimmed down
from over-grieving.
After all, His Majesty treated Consort Vertu generously.
Her funeral followed the protocol for a Noble Consort.
And His Majesty placed Princess Jinghe under Your Highness's care.
How's your shifu?
Shifu has lost his spirit
ever since he disabled his body.
All he does is drink alcohol.
What's the point of recognizing one's deep affection
when the person is gone?
Look after him for me.
Yes, Your Highness.
Given Wen Shichu's condition,
the only doctor I can rely on
is you.
I thank Your Highness for your appreciation.
I will put forth my best effort.
It's best if you truly will.
I won't treat you unfairly.
Ask Wen Shichu to come here in a few days,
to take Princess Jinghe's pulse.
You know how to make the request properly.
I understand, Your Highness.
Your Highness, if there's no other orders,
I shall take my leave.
Yes.
I thank Your Highness.
Peace to Your Noble Highness.
Please rise, Mr. Su.
Your Highness, His Majesty has a gift,
Is the Second Lady here?
She's in the Empress Dowager's palace.
Then please receive this gift for the Second Lady, Your Highness.
His Majesty granted a pair of twin begonia tassels -
representing two sisters.
They are newly crafted by palace jewelers.
To reward the Second Lady for her courage when
protecting Your Noble Highness in the Empress’s palace.
Please thank His Majesty profusely on my behalf.
Allow me to take my leave.
Have Sparrow's posthumous matters been taken care of?
Everything's taken care of.
But My Lady, why are you only worrying about Sparrow
at this moment?
Well then, what am I supposed to be worried about?
My Lady, His Majesty hasn't been here
for quite some days now.
Aren't you worried?
Are you planning to do anything?
What is there to be worried about?
I'm not the only one His Majesty is avoiding.
He's busy grieving over Consort Vertu.
But you can rest assured,
he won't be sad for too many days.
I know His Majesty all too well.
However, in all due respect, My lady.
Even if Consort Vertu did not die,
she would never be in our way.
Whether she had to die or not,
she was ... so close to Zhen Huan...
Only her death
would sadden Zhen Huan to death.
Only seeing Zhen Huan's misery
can I finally be purged of the insult I swallowed.
Sister Vertu,
suppose you did die in vain ...
this cup of wine ...
is my respect for you.
Don't forget to tell the judge of the underworld that
Zhen Huan was the one who really killed you.
I don't remember granting you
Cui Bai's painting "Autumn Reeds, Hibiscuses and Geese".
This is my little sister's doodle.
Did it fool Your Majesty?
Your sister who strode into the Empress's Palace?
She hasn't thanked me for the jewelry I gifted her yet.
She can't delay further, since I'm here in your palace.
Peace to Your Majesty.
Do you dislike the tassels I granted you?
You aren't wearing them.
She doesn't like gold and jewelry.
That's why she never put them on.
You haven't thanked His Majesty yet.
Not only do I dislike gold and jewelry,
the begonia flowers on the tassels
are my sister's favorite flowers.
I would never infringe on her favored things.
Never mind then.
You are talented at painting.
Would you like to explore your skills with the palace artists?
I can arrange that for you.
The palace artists prefer opulent colors in their paintings.
Your Majesty saw my replication of Cui Bai's painting
and should know the palace artists and I
aren't likely to have an agreeable session.
Your drawing of the wild geese is very good.
I like birds that represent loyalty.
Go to the Ruyi Pavilion when you get a chance.
You can retrieve the original painting of
"Autumn Reeds, Hibiscuses and Geese".
Both Yunli and Yunxi like this painting.
They've asked me to give it to them many times.
I'm granting it to you right now.
I thank Your Majesty.
This painting has an auspicious implication.
I hope Yurao won't be far away from me after she gets married one day.
Just like the geese are close to the hibiscus flowers in the painting,
I hope to always live near to my sister.
How coincidental!
I would say "Enemies always meet on a narrow road."
Well, you can never avoid your enemies.
His Majesty rewarded you
"Autumn Reeds, Hibiscuses and Geese"?
To make my sister happy.
I requested this painting from His Majesty many times
but he was always reluctant.
After all, he appreciates Her Noble Highness the most.
So you also like this painting?
Particularly the pair of geese, more than everything else.
"Through the evening snow on the thousand mountains,"
"Through the evening snow on the thousand mountains,
to whom should the widowed goose fly?"
You also like to read lyric poetry?
Yuan Haowen only had this one good poem.
Geese are birds of loyalty.
That's why I like them.
By the way, thank you for helping my sister the other night.
Don't thank me. I felt obliged to.
But it took quite a while to hear you say "thank you".
If you really mean to thank me,
can you let me admire the details of this painting?
Sure.
Cui Bai abandoned the sumptuous style
of the court painters in the Northern Song Dynasty
in favor of greater realism.
The result is this lifelike painting.
It turns out that you aren't entirely a
"learn nothing, know nothing."
"Learn nothing, know nothing"?
How about we have a painting competition?
Sure, what should we paint?
Let's paint ... the spring scenery.
Certainly.
We are going to the Ruyi Pavilion.
Aye.
I heard that His Majesty has been neglecting Concubine An.
Yet the Empress has gotten away with everything.
His Majesty forgave her so easily.
It's as if he can't distinguish between right and wrong!
Of course His Majesty knows right from wrong, but he also
cares about Empress Première and the Empress Dowager.
His decision didn't reflect his own will.
Wen Shichu bids peace to Your Noble Highness.
I smelled alcohol before you even came in.
It might disturb Jinghe.
A man with a dead heart ... wouldn't care about washing and dressing nicely.
Hold her in your arms.
She has gained some weight.
The princess is very healthy.
I thank Your Highness for taking good care of her.
No matter how much I take care of her,
I can't replace her parents.
Jinghe cries loudly at dawn every day.
I wonder if it's because she misses Meizhuang.
On the day when Meizhuang was encoffined,
I put my heirloom jade teapot in her coffin.
Perhaps I should have given her the jade teapot earlier.
I was so stupid ... to have made her rueful for so many years.
In this life ...
I owe her so much.
Although Meizhuang is gone, you still have Jinghe.
You have to plan for the child.
Are you going to keep drinking every day?
I can never forget
the feeling when she passed away in my arms.
Huan'er,
I developed the habit of looking out for you,
and it's hard to change any habit.
But for Meizhuang,
I could feel her loneliness and struggle in the harem
as if it was my own.
She cared for me in the same way I had been for you.
I have requested that His Majesty
send me to guard her "catalpa palace" [coffin] for three years
as punishment for failing in my duty.
I understand, Shichu.
But the dead have passed on.
The living have to live on and bear it all.
You must live well, so that Meizhuang
can find consolation "under the Yellow Spring".
Since Consort Vertu's death,
His Majesty has only visited the Palace of Prolonging Happiness once
and he left after sitting down briefly.
I know what you're trying to say.
Feel the walls and the floor of the Palace of Great Benevolence.
They are as cold as an icehouse.
It's already past the Dragon Boat Festival.
His Majesty hasn't even visited once.
You have to earn the favor you deserve.
Or, do you think I can drag His Majesty to sit in your palace?
Rest assured, Your Majesty.
Each day I'm alive,
Noble Consort Lumière won't have it so easy.
All right.
I've been helping you because I have expectations for you.
Don't disappoint my expectations.
What Your Majesty expects is what I look forward to.
His Majesty the Emperor.
I bow before Your Majesty.
- Rise.
- Peace and grace to Your Majesty.
Please rise.
You are always sensitive to the heat.
I should've taken you to the Summer Palace to escape the heat.
"Only the housekeeper knows the costs of charcoal and rice."
Her Majesty the Empress Dowager is feeling unwell
and shouldn't go for a long trip.
And it's not easy to travel with all these children under my care
and a mass of maids and wet nurses.
We would also need to have the Summer Palace rearranged.
Then the money will flow away like the running river.
You've been frugal.
I reviewed the palace expenses for this month.
They went down over seven thousand taels over last month.
That's the merit of your frugality.
It's too early to be glad, Your Majesty.
If Your Majesty selects several new concubines one day,
even ten thousand taels won't cover the cost.
I sense some sourness in your words.
If you want to save money on that,
I can tell you the trick.
How about I promote several maids from your palace to Companions,
and their monthly stipends will be deducted from your stipend.
Your Majesty can marry whoever pleases you.
It's not rare to have several new Companions.
If someone really catches your eye,
you should promote her directly to Noble Lady.
If you are so generous, how about I marry Jade today?
What do you think?
Jade is my only dowry maid now.
Is Your Majesty going to take her away from me?
It's exactly because she has your trust
that I must treat her generously.
How about granting her the title of Attendant,
just like when you entered the palace?
I'll name her Attendant Xi [Auspicious].
Translators: The Magpie Bridge Brigade 鹊桥小队翻译组
https://magpiebridgebrigade.cn
Twitter/FB/IG @BrigadeMagpie 公众号/微博: 鹊桥小队翻译组
Theme: The Phoenix Taking Flight
[phoenix is the symbol of an empress]
The dreams I dimly recall;
The past I hardly remember,
amidst the autumn moons and the spring flowers.
Like the moon's reflection on water
or flowers seen through mist - floating and drifting.
The joyous sounds you brought;
The silence you left;
Changing faster than clouds can turn to rain.
Our minds resonated;
Our hearts beat in unison;
But we lost what we once possessed.
A poem to converse;
A melody to accompany;
A heart to bind to mine.
I hoped for endless longing and eternal promise,
but I’m left with only the flute and the zither.
With affection, I pleased;
With my heart, I committed;
With my arms, I embraced.
I desired to be remembered;
Desired to be cherished;
Why am I only hated and deceived?
My wish ran against my will.
Behold the mockery of destiny and the game of fate.
My unwavering love is gone
like flowers swept away in the wind.
Praying for a bright moon;
Praying for a rising sun;
Dreaming to bask in the spring breezes.
But the unsparing northern winds carry snow and rain
to destroy the aspirations of the plum tree.
A phoenix about to take flight rustles its wings
but the arc of its flight is unseen.
The phoenix tree sways in the wind,
shedding memories in the whispers of the falling leaves.